window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Linear_Algebra — Slot 2 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Linear_Algebra — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>If \\(x+2 y=30\\),then \\(\\left(\\frac{2 y}{5}+\\frac{x}{3}\\right)+\\left(\\frac{x}{5}+\\frac{2 y}{3}\\right)\\) will be equal to <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>16</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>18</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>16</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331481/isro2020-55\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let A and B be two nxn matrices over real numbers. Let rank(M) and det(M) denote the rank and determinant of a matrix M, respectively. Consider the following statements. <br><br>\nI.    rank(AB)=rank (A)rank (B)<br>\nII.  det(AB)=det(A)det(B)<br>\nIII. rank(A+B) \\(\\leq\\) rank (A) + rank (B)<br>\nIV. det(A+B) \\(\\leq\\) det(A) + det(B)<br><br>\nWhich of the above statements are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333204/gate2020-cs-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following matrix:  <br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 4 &amp; 8\\\\ 1&amp; 3 &amp; 9 &amp;27 \\\\ 1 &amp; 4 &amp; 16 &amp;64 \\\\ 1 &amp; 5 &amp; 25 &amp;125 \\end{bmatrix}\\)<br> The absolute value of the product of Eigenvalues of R is _________ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "12",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302804/gate2019-cs-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let X be a square matrix. Consider the following two statements on X.<br><br>\nI. X is invertible<br>\nII. Determinant of X is non-zero <br><br>\nWhich one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I implies II; II does not imply I</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II implies I; I does not imply II</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I does not imply II; II does not imply I</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I and II are equivalent statements</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I and II are equivalent statements</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302839/gate2019-cs-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider a matrix P whose only eigenvectors are the multiples of \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1\\\\ 4 \\end{bmatrix}\\). <br>\nConsider the following statements. <br>\n(I) P does not have an inverse <br>\n(II) P has a repeated eigenvalue <br>\n(III) P cannot be diagonalized <br>\nWhich one of the following options is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only I and III are necessarily true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only II is necessarily true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only I and II are necessarily true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only II and III are necessarily true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Only II and III are necessarily true</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204100/gate2018-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider a matrix \\(A=uv^{T}\\; where \\; u=\\begin{bmatrix} 1\\\\ 2 \\end{bmatrix},v=\\begin{bmatrix} 1\\\\ 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\)  Note that \\(v^{T}\\)  denotes the transpose of v. The largest eigenvalue of A is _____. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "3",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204091/gate2018-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>If A is a skew symmetric matrix then \\(A^{t}\\)  is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Diagonal matrix</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-A</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>-A</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128505/isro2017-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>If the characteristics polynomial of 3x3 matrix M over R ( the set of real numbers) is\n\\(\\lambda ^{3}-4\\lambda ^{2}+a\\lambda +30,a\\in R\\), and one eigenvalue of M is 2, then the largest among the absolute values of the eigenvalues of M is ________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118618/gate2017-2-52#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider a quadratic equation \\(x^{2} -13x +36 = 0\\) with coefficients in a base b. The solutions of this equation in the same base b are x = 5 and x = 6. Then b = ___________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "8",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118185/gate2017-2-24#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(P=\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 1&amp;-1 \\\\ 2&amp;-3 &amp; 4\\\\ 3 &amp;-2 &amp; 3 \\end{bmatrix} \\) and \\( Q=\\begin{bmatrix} -1 &amp; -2&amp;-1 \\\\ 6 &amp; 12&amp; 6\\\\ 5&amp;10 &amp; 5 \\end{bmatrix}\\) be two matrices.\nThen the rank of P +Q is _____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "2",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118363/gate2017-2-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Let A be nxn real valued square symmetric matrix of rank 2 with \\(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}\\sum_{j=1}^{n}A^{2}_{ij}=50\\). Consider\nthe following statements. <br> <br>(I) One eigen value must be in [-5, 5]   <br>      (II) The eigen value with the largest magnitude must be strictly greater than 5. <br> <br>\nWhich of the above statements about eigen values of A is/are necessarily CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (I) and (II)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(I) only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(II) only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (I) nor (II)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>(I) only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118312/gate2017-1-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(c_{1}....c_{n}\\)  be scalars, not all zero, such that \\(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}c_{i}a_{i}=0\\)<br> where \\(a_{i}\\) are column vectors in \\(R^{n}\\). Consider the set of linear equations Ax = b <br>\nwhere A=\\(a_{1}....a_{n}\\) and b=\\(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}a_{i}\\). The set of equations has <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a unique solution at  \\(x=J_{n}\\) where \\(J_{n}\\) denotes a n-dimensional vector of all 1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>no solution</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>infinitely many solutions</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>finitely many solutions</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>infinitely many solutions</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118282/gate2017-1-3#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that the eigen values of matrix A are 1, 2, 4. The determinant of \\((A^{-1})^{T}\\) is _________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.124",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39549/gate2016-2-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the systems,each consisting of m linear equations in n variables.<br>\nI. If m \\(\\lt\\) n, then all such systems have a solution <br>\nII. If m \\(\\gt\\) n, then none of these systems has a solution <br>\nIII. If m = n, then there exists a system which has a solution <br>\nWhich one of the following is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I, II and III are true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only II and III are true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only III is true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of them is true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Only III is true</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39554/gate2016-2-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>The coefficient of \\(x^{12}\\) in \\((x^{3}+x^{4}+x^{5}+x^{6}+. . .)^{3}\\) is ______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "10",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39693/gate2016-1-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
